<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>All Posts - Keep Thinking</title>
        <link>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/</link>
        <description>All Posts | Keep Thinking</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 00:00:00 &#43;0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://keepthinking.blog/posts/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>The Real Age of Propaganda</title>
    <link>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/real-age-of-propaganda/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Mykhaylo Beliansky</author>
    <guid>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/real-age-of-propaganda/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>There is a great book on propaganda. It&rsquo;s called <a href="https://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/age-of-propaganda-anthony-pratkanis/1119469522" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">The Age of Propaganda</a>
. It&rsquo;s a very worthy book that I sincerely recommend.</p>

<p>But when you hear the word propaganda, don&rsquo;t you think of it as of something from the past? You think of nazi Germany and those long speeches in black-and-white.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not something that happens today. And in a way you are right.</p>
<p>That propaganda was small (only one country) and cozy (only one language). Yes, they tried to influence other countries, but it was a small effort. It was like selling hand-crafted products by mail order.</p>
<p>Today&rsquo;s thing is like AliExpress selling cheap industrial goods online.</p>
<h2 id="the-real-thing">The Real Thing</h2>
<p>The real age of propaganda is just starting. It&rsquo;s the only thing that Russia does well in the war against Ukraine. And it&rsquo;s something HAMAS is exceptionally good in the war against Israel (not without Russia&rsquo;s help, apparently).</p>
<p>Propaganda of the 20th century is kindergarten play compared to what we see today. Today&rsquo;s product is not hand crafted, it&rsquo;s mass-produced at fully automated AI factories operated by a few smart people. It&rsquo;s not small and cozy, it&rsquo;s huge and it&rsquo;s exported everywhere. Today&rsquo;s delivery of propaganda abroad is not mail-order of hand-crafted goods, it&rsquo;s Amazon and AliExpress scale logistics of millions of mass produced cheap products.</p>
<figure style="float: right; margin-left: 20px; width: 50%; margin-bottom: 20px">

<figcaption style="text-align: left">HAMAS actor as a fighter, injured, press, patient, mourning father</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The effect is devastating to human mind a spirit. The simple wrong answers were always easier to accept, but there were never so many to choose from. And <strong>nobody cares if the answers they are consuming are true</strong>.</p>
<p>In case of HAMAS it&rsquo;s especially easy to see. HAMAS is a terrorist organization, we all know that. It&rsquo;s basically controlling the entire Gaza region. <strong>Who in their right mind would ever expect to hear a single word of truth out of them?</strong></p>
<p>I mean you need motivation to say the truth instead of lying to everybody to your full advantage. In democracies you have free press, you have more or less independent prosecution systems, you have free speech where somebody might uncover something and make it public. This give at least some motivation to not lie.</p>
<figure style="float: left; margin-right: 20px; width: 50%; margin-bottom: 20px">

<figcaption style="text-align: left">Presumably independent reporter kissed by one of HAMAS leaders</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Obviously any dictatorship will use any truth it can in propaganda. Truth is more convincing when it plays along. But it&rsquo;s like with the famous saying that even a broken watch show correct time twice a day.</p>
<p>The scary thing the people see the photos like the ones shown — with the same actor playing a distressed citizen, a fighter, a mourning father, and injured civilian, a doctor and a reporter. And people read stories that presumably independent reporters were magically present at the border when HAMAS breached it. And it changes nothing.</p>
<p>Emotionally they were already bought by propaganda. And no amount of truth will change their mindset. Because propaganda is not trying to convince, it&rsquo;s trying to create an emotion.</p>
<p>And once it succeeded&hellip; it&rsquo;s not afraid of truth any more.</p>
<p>HAMAS is openly saying <em>&ldquo;we used the money received as aid from developed nations to build underground tunnels and weapons. Protection of civilians is the task of UN&rdquo;</em>. And does it affect their popularity? No. Because the emotional link is already there &ldquo;Israelis are killing civilians&rdquo;.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LoOH4R3HrUw?si=fU_Xklp1UhVamLvh" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>People are rallying on the streets because of the <em>&ldquo;humanitarian crisis unseen in the last 80 years&rdquo;</em> demanding cease-fire.</p>
<p>But it&rsquo;s not true. It&rsquo;s not unseen. The scale of the humanitarian tragedy in Israel and Palestine is simply incomparable to what is happening in Ukraine. The death toll of the war Russia is waging against Ukraine is in the <em>hundred thousands</em>. Entire cities were erased from the face of the earth. There are more landmines than ever in human history anywhere. And it&rsquo;s much, much closer to Europe.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EDJVeO_Mw0g?si=ElrT236ibYK1Vdzt" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>Yet we don&rsquo;t see such scale of protests on the streets. Why? Because Ukraine sucks at informational warfare and Russia is good at it. Russia has been pouring millions into propaganda everywhere and helping HAMAS along the way. Nobody cares about a full-scale war at their doorstep any more.</p>
<p><strong>Humans can only worry about one thing at a time. So while they are worrying about Israel killing Palestinian children they are not worrying about Russia killing and kidnapping Ukrainian children on a much larger scale.</strong></p>
<p>It looks like democracies are just worse at propaganda than the dictatorships are, just like reasonable politicians are less popular than the extremist populists.</p>
<p>And that&rsquo;s really bad news.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Useful Idiots: Lars von Trier</title>
    <link>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/useful-idiot-lars-von-trier/</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Mykhaylo Beliansky</author>
    <guid>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/useful-idiot-lars-von-trier/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>With this post I&rsquo;m starting a new section on this blog about <a href="https://keepthinking.blog/tags/useful-idiots" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer"><strong>useful idiots</strong></a>
.</p>
<p>I intend to write about celebrities, opinion leaders etc. that are used by Russian propaganda with them having no clue (differently from people who are obviously Russian assets). I plan to write a more detailed post on the history of the term &ldquo;useful idiot&rdquo; in the future.</p>
<p>So today we look at an <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CwQF70VMWS3/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">instagram post</a>
 by renowned Danish director Lars von Trier:</p>

<p>The post reads:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>By the way:
To Mr. Zelenskyj and Mr. Putin, and not least Mrs. Frederiksen (who yesterday, like someone head over heels in love, posed in the cockpit of one of the scariest killing machines of our time, grinning from ear to ear):</p>
<p>“RUSSIAN LIVES MATTER ALSO!”</p>
<p>Best regards Lars</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Interesting point Mr. von Trier. So when Russians bomb our cities we shouldn&rsquo;t defend ourselves because we should care about Russian lives.</p>
<p>What about an extremely simple way of protecting Russian lives: getting out of Ukraine?</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not the victim&rsquo;s fault that the attacker got injured while attacking. It&rsquo;s the victim&rsquo;s <em>achievement</em>.</p>
<p>So if you want to protect Russian lives then help us stop the war, not put your influence behind their aggression.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>On Russian Military Traditions</title>
    <link>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/war-crimes/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Mykhaylo Beliansky</author>
    <guid>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/war-crimes/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Mastodon user @kravietz@agora.echelon.pt wrote a small <a href="https://agora.echelon.pl/objects/5ee2533d-a0be-4e30-b797-5546341dd5d9" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">post</a>
 on how the Russian army behaved during the Afghan war of 1979-89 quoting soldier memoirs<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, noting that nothing has changed in their behavior and they still act the same today:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In the village one of the sergeants remarked, without hiding his emotion, that &rsquo;the young women are good&rsquo;. The sergeant&rsquo;s words set all the others on fire like a spark, and then he threw off his overcoat and moved on one of the women: — Row, lads! In front of the aksakals and the children, our internationalists had their way with the women. The rape went on for two hours. The children huddled in a corner, screaming and shrieking, trying to help their mothers somehow. The old men, trembling, prayed to their God for mercy and salvation. Then the sergeant commanded, &ldquo;Fire!&rdquo; - and was the first to shoot the woman he had just raped. Quickly they finished off all the others as well. Then they poured fuel from the tank of the infantry fighting vehicle, poured it all over the dead bodies, covered them with some clothes, rags and even the scanty wooden furniture and set them on fire. The flames flared up inside the adobe&hellip;&quot;.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There is no surprise for me in nothing changing in thirty short years because nothing changed for hundreds of years. Let&rsquo;s compare the very fresh quote above with this quote from the pillar of Russian literature Leo Tolstoy<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> describing the war of the mid-nineteenth century:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The aoul<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> which had been destroyed was that in which Haji Murad had spent the night before he went over to the Russians. Sado and his family had left the aoul on the approach of the Russian detachment, and when he returned he found his saklya<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> in ruins &ndash; the roof fallen in, the door and the posts supporting the penthouse burned, and the interior filthy. His son, the handsome bright-eyed boy who had gazed with such ecstasy at Haji Murad, was brought dead to the mosque on a horse covered with a barka; he had been stabbed in the back with a bayonet. The dignified woman who had served Haji Murad when he was at the house now stood over her son&rsquo;s body, her smock torn in front, her withered old breasts exposed, her hair down, and she dug her hails into her face till it bled, and wailed incessantly. Sado, taking a pick-ax and spade, had gone with his relatives to dig a grave for his son. The old grandfather sat by the wall of the ruined saklya cutting a stick and gazing stolidly in front of him. He had only just returned from the apiary. The two stacks of hay there had been burnt, the apricot and cherry trees he had planted and reared were broken and scorched, and worse still all the beehives and bees had been burnt. The wailing of the women and the little children, who cried with their mothers, mingled with the lowing of the hungry cattle for whom there was no food. The bigger children, instead of playing, followed their elders with frightened eyes. The fountain was polluted, evidently on purpose, so that the water could not be used. The mosque was polluted in the same way, and the Mullah and his assistants were cleaning it out. No one spoke of hatred of the Russians. The feeling experienced by all the Chechens, from the youngest to the oldest, was stronger than hate. It was not hatred, for they did not regard those Russian dogs as human beings, but it was such repulsion, disgust, and perplexity at the senseless cruelty of these creatures, that the desire to exterminate them &ndash; like the desire to exterminate rats, poisonous spiders, or wolves &ndash; was as natural an instinct as that of self-preservation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Russians are right when they are claiming that they are a country of ancient traditions. I&rsquo;m quite sure we could trace this kind of tradition even further back in time, maybe all the way to the Golden Horde.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><a href="http://afghan-war-soldiers.ru/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Soldiers of Afghan War (Russian Language)</a>
&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p><a href="https://mthoyibi.files.wordpress.com/2011/03/hadji-murad_leo-tolstoy.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer"><em>Haji Murad</em></a>
 by Leo Tolstoy, Chapter XVII&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>village&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>house&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>On Small Propaganda Tricks</title>
    <link>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/propaganda-tricks-1/</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Mykhaylo Beliansky</author>
    <guid>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/propaganda-tricks-1/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-inspiration">The Inspiration</h2>
<p>I had a short <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@yogthos@lemmy.ml/110672976582947303" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">discussion</a>
 on Mastodon today that started with this post:</p>

<p>Since this was a stone thrown at Ukraine I had to participate.</p>
<p>But this blog post and this blog is not about Ukraine but about thinking, so let&rsquo;s look at this at a slightly different angle, which does not require us to take sides in the immediate discussion about Ukraine, Canadian aid or land ownership, but rather explains a trick that is used by propagandists all over the world so much, that it&rsquo;s probably one of the oldest and most used in the book. It&rsquo;s also one of the most effective.</p>
<p>If you read the post again and ask yourself: what is this about? The answer is obvious: it&rsquo;s about the impact of some Canadian aid program on land privatization in Ukraine. Personally, I have no idea what aid program he&rsquo;s referring to. But that&rsquo;s not the point. And it&rsquo;s also not the point of this &ldquo;toot&rdquo; (as they call posts on Mastodon).</p>
<h2 id="the-distraction">The Distraction</h2>
<p>You see, the reference to the Canadian aid program is a distraction. As any illusionist would tell you, in order to pull off a trick you need to distract viewers attention to a place where nothing is actually happening, while you do your thing in another place altogether.</p>
<p>Frankly, most people don&rsquo;t care about the Canadian aid to Ukraine and even it&rsquo;s impact on Ukrainian land ownership. But even if they do, they&rsquo;ll either agree or disagree with it, and that would mean they got distracted.</p>
<h2 id="the-trick">The Trick</h2>
<p>The real trick that the author wants you to just not pay attention to, and therefore accept without critical evaluation, is in the word <em><strong>coup</strong></em>.</p>
<p>You see, we don&rsquo;t call a positive political event a coup.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>coup</strong> a sudden decisive exercise of force in politics and especially the violent overthrow or alteration of an existing government by a small group (<a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/coup" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Merriam-Webster</a>
)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sudden<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, decisive, violent overthrow by a small group of people<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. Also violent, apparently. There is also the emotional attitude that the word carries. A coup is something planned behind closed doors and executed by violent people in palaces. It&rsquo;s something that happens in countries you wouldn&rsquo;t want to visit even in the best of days.</p>
<p>So while the poster distracts your attention by seemingly talking about Canandian aid, he is in fact smuggling a very emotionally charged and negative description to the events in Ukraine into your mind. With a single four-letter word. Not bad.</p>
<p>Now, you have the full right to agree or disagree with his description, but if you want to be thinking critically you need to <em>notice</em> it and ask yourself: wait a moment, do I actually agree that it was a coup and not a revolution, a peaceful protest, a democratic protest, an act of direct democracy by the people?</p>
<p>Maybe you&rsquo;ll need to do some reading, maybe you&rsquo;re just not interested. But if you noticed it - you didn&rsquo;t get tricked.</p>
<p>As I said before this trick is extremely effective and used a lot both in print and during speeches and debates. Now you know about it.</p>
<h2 id="update">UPDATE</h2>
<p>After I published this post and got some comments on it, I have managed to find an even better example of the same trick by the same poster.</p>

<p>This example is even better than the first one, so I had to update the post. Look what&rsquo;s going on here:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a clear double standard between the media hysteria over alleged Russian atrocities in Ukraine and the silence over the rampages by Israeli troops and settlers on the occupied West Bank.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Take a moment yourself and try to point out, where is the distraction and where is the trick?</p>
<p>So the distraction is the whole part about media having double standards, and the trick, as always is in details. You see, while you&rsquo;re thinking about Israel and your position on what&rsquo;s going on there the poster is smuggling two very charged words: <strong>hysteria</strong> and <strong>alleged</strong>.</p>
<p>Neat, ha? If this wasn&rsquo;t propaganda I would almost admire the cunning and elegance. So the media reaction to the largest war since WW2 with literally thousands over thousands of documented war crimes is called &ldquo;hysteria&rdquo; and the crimes themselves are &ldquo;alleged&rdquo;, unproven, maybe non-existent.</p>
<p>As I said before, your opinion on the subject is your business. But for the sake of critical thinking you have to notice these words being smuggled while you&rsquo;re distracted.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Euromaidan lasted 3 months and 1 day. Does this count as sudden? <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euromaidan" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Wiki</a>
&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Does this group of people seem small and violent? Five hundered thousand Ukrainians singing national anthem during the 2013 revolution <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RTHpSnrKEeA" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">YouTube</a>
&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Elon Musk and the Magic of Names</title>
    <link>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/elon-musk-and-the-magic-of-names/</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Mykhaylo Beliansky</author>
    <guid>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/elon-musk-and-the-magic-of-names/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday a strange thing happened. You have probably seen it:</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to concentrate on all the ways posting this was wrong. I expect there will be a shit storm strong enough without my five cents. In the spirit of this blog I&rsquo;m more interested in the questions relating to thinking and knowledge. And there&rsquo;s an obvious one.</p>
<h1 id="how-do-we-know-that-we-really-know-what-we-think-we-know">How do we know that we really know what we think we know?</h1>
<p>Wow that&rsquo;s a stunning example of a well-formulated question right there.</p>
<p>I admit, I&rsquo;m kinda using Elon Musk here as a screaming example of publicly talking about things you have no clue about. But we&rsquo;re all guilty at times of doing the same. Even if we&rsquo;re not public.</p>
<p>But let&rsquo;s keep using him as an example. There must be some foundation under his opinion about Crimea: after all, he confidently states that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Crimea formally part of Russia, as it has been since 1783 (until Khrushchev’s mistake).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And there lies the trap that most people will fall into. They will try fact checking this statement, reading the Wiki article on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crimea" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Crimea</a>
, trying to figure out was it really formally a part of Russia. Reading and arguing about how Crimean Khanate was conquered and if Crimea wanted to be a part of Russia.</p>
<p>And they will totally miss the elephant in the room. The &ldquo;Russia&rdquo; he talks about doesn&rsquo;t exist. And it didn&rsquo;t exist for over a century.</p>
<h2 id="wait-what">Wait what?</h2>
<p>This little thought was nagging me for a long time, maybe 10 or even 20 years, and I could never put my finger exactly on it. Until I did.</p>
<p>Being Ukrainian, for me this was kind of obvious<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> on an intuitive level. But until today I didn&rsquo;t see it for what it was — the most ingenious piece of Russian propaganda.</p>
<h3 id="its-all-in-the-name">It&rsquo;s all in the name</h3>
<p>Long time ago there was a country called &ldquo;Russia&rdquo;. Well, maybe there was such country, it&rsquo;s hard to tell by now, after rewriting history so many times. But there definitely was a country called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_Empire" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer"><em>Russian Empire</em></a>
, and we can tell exactly when it started.</p>
<p>The term and the entire ideology was coined by a Ukrainian<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> scholar <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theophan_Prokopovich" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Theophan Prokopovich (ukr. Феофан Прокопович)</a>
, a very educated guy lacking any moral compass. After Peter I tried destroying <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_University_of_Kyiv-Mohyla_Academy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Kyiv Mohyla Academy</a>
, the only real university in the region of that time, he promoted Theophan to some important role in Saint Petersburg. There he coined the whole concept of Russian <em>Empire</em>, following a good European tradition of claiming to be the <em>Third Rome</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.</p>
<p>In any case, in 1721 he renamed the Tsardom of Russia into Russian <strong>Empire</strong>, and that&rsquo;s when the country officially started. And that country was normally referred to as <strong>Russia</strong> in the West. That&rsquo;s important.</p>
<p>Before World War I it was a pretty big country. As Elon Musk says, Crimea was formally it&rsquo;s part. As were other nice places, like Poland, Finland and all the Baltic states.</p>
<p>Right until it stopped existing.</p>
<h3 id="the-great-october-revolution">The &ldquo;Great October Revolution&rdquo;</h3>
<p>You need to understand, that I&rsquo;m doing this as quickly as I can before I get you bored. We&rsquo;re almost there.</p>
<p>In 1917 after a series of revolutions caused by the terrible decision to participate in the Great War, there finally seemed to be a clear revolutionary winner — the Bolshevik Party, which later became the Communist Party.</p>
<p>And they wanted nothing to do with the former Imperial past. They renamed the country into <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soviet_Union" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer"><em>Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</em></a>
, also known as the <em>Soviet Union</em>. And that was the country I was born in.</p>
<p>Some places got lucky and broke off early, when this abomination of a state was just forming: like Finland. Others tried, but didn&rsquo;t succeed, like Ukraine<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.</p>
<p>But even those places that didn&rsquo;t succeed, were not part of Russia. They were part of the Soviet Union. Multinational. Multicultural. Calling themselves &ldquo;soviet people&rdquo;. Not &ldquo;Russians&rdquo;.</p>
<p>USSR was a scary country with a scary ideology, and we&rsquo;re all lucky it didn&rsquo;t survive the Cold War. But until it&rsquo;s later days that country had principles. I don&rsquo;t agree with it&rsquo;s ideology, but it had one. I don&rsquo;t agree with the future it wanted to build for the humanity, but it was looking into the <em>future</em>.</p>
<p>That country fought in World War II and a bunch of other wars. That country was one of the founding states of United Nations and a permanent member of the UN Security Council.</p>
<p>Right until it stopped existing in 1991.</p>
<h3 id="devils-work">Devil&rsquo;s work</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>The Devil’s cleverest wile is to make men believe that he does not exist.  &ndash; Charles Baudelaire</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Modern day Russia is like that, but it tries to convince the world (and itself), that it&rsquo;s somehow, magically, the same country as USSR and Russian Empire. The whole idea behind <em>rashism</em> is trying to bring back the past, not to build some brighter version of the future (even if it doesn&rsquo;t seem brighter to everybody else, like in the case of the USSR).</p>
<p>And it&rsquo;s not the first time something like this happens in a dictatorship. Mussolini used to address the Italians as <em>Romans</em>, and insisted that his Italy was magically the same country as the Roman Empire.</p>
<p>So saying that Crimea was part of Russia, and should be left to Russia is like saying that Greece was a part of the Roman Empire, and should be left to Italy.</p>
<p><strong>And the only reason it doesn&rsquo;t sound absurd is because during the Soviet times we kept calling the country &ldquo;Russia&rdquo;.</strong></p>
<h2 id="returning-to-the-original-question">Returning to the original question</h2>
<p>So how do we know that we really know what we think we know? I&rsquo;m afraid this question is so big, that it&rsquo;s impossible to cover in an essay. But there are some tricks we can use:</p>
<h3 id="look-for-alternative-points-of-view-and-alternative-sources">Look for alternative points of view and alternative sources</h3>
<p>And by point of view I don&rsquo;t just mean &ldquo;opinions&rdquo;, but also other angles to look at a the subject. Because if the subject is even a slightly bit controversial (and most interesting subjects are), and you only used one source — by definition you only heard one side of the story.</p>
<h3 id="question-fundamentals">Question fundamentals</h3>
<p>Try questioning the most fundamental parts of the subject. Like with the Musks tweet the fundamental part was not whether Crimea is or is not part of Russia, but in fact whether the &ldquo;Russia&rdquo; he talks about even exists.</p>
<p>I hope you enjoyed the ride.</p>
<hr>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If something seems &ldquo;obvious&rdquo; it&rsquo;s a true sign that almost everybody else sees it differently&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Fate is a bitch&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Read up on <em>translatio imperii</em>, but read something good&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Read up on <em>Ukrainians People&rsquo;s Republic</em>&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Why write?</title>
    <link>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/why-write/</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Mykhaylo Beliansky</author>
    <guid>https://keepthinking.blog/posts/why-write/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Writing is a tool. And as any good tool it can be used for many things. Sharing information. Telling stories. Messaging. Influencing people to make the choice you want them to make. All these uses were clear to me for a long time, and they all were pretty self-explanatory.</p>
<p>There was one special use though, that I was wondering about for a long time.</p>
<h1 id="writing-helps-you-think">Writing helps you think.</h1>
<p>A couple of days ago I was flying from Lisbon to Krakow, first part of my journey to my home in Ukraine (why go there during the war is another story).</p>
<p>Right before the take off I stumbled upon an essay by <a href="http://paulgraham.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Paul Graham</a>
 called, ironically, <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/essay.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer"><em>The Age of the Essay</em></a>
. As brilliant people often do, he put in words precisely the things I felt for a long time.</p>
<p>I recommend you read his original piece, as he did a great job about describing the history and the essence of writing essays. But I will quote one thing:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In a real essay you&rsquo;re writing for yourself. You&rsquo;re thinking out loud.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But not quite. Just as inviting people over forces you to clean up your apartment, writing something that other people will read forces you to think well.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And this really stroke a note inside. I knew for a long time that writing helps me think. I even joked sometimes that you need to sit down and write on the subject to find out what your real opinion is.</p>
<p>But reading Graham&rsquo;s piece changed two things:</p>
<ol>
<li>This kind of writing now had a name. Essays.</li>
<li>It gave me a good reason to publish what I write.</li>
</ol>
<p>And now you&rsquo;re here. Reading.</p>
<p>Thank you for giving me a reason to clean up my mess!</p>
]]></description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
